Thiago de Paula Oliveira

R, Shiny, Maple, SageMath **▶** Statistical computing:

▶ Computational programs: Latex, Markdown, Office, Gimp, Inkscape, Github

▶ Operational systems: Linux, Windows

▶ Languages: Portuguese (native), English (upper intermediate)

ORCID, Plubons ▶ Research web pages:



Thiago is a Senior Biostatistician at Orreco working in partnership with the Insight Centre for Data Analytics and National University of Ireland Galway (NUIGalway). His expertise is in statistical modelling, in particular the study of individual level responses over time. Thiago holds a PhD in Statistics from the University of São Paulo, Brazil. He has over six years experience in all aspects of statistical modelling and has published several peer-reviewed papers. Before joining Orreco, Thiago was Assistant Professor and postdoctoral researcher at the University of São Paulo. During his undergraduate, he was enjoyed in a project granted by São Paulo Research Foundation, and involving the Biological Sciences and Exact Sciences Departments. This project led to publication of two peer-review papers, and a conference paper which won honorable mention by the University of São Paulo. His research interests comprise longitudinal data, concordance analysis, response prediction, generalized linear mixed-effects model, computing for statistical development (specially in R software), experimental designs, observational study, development of dashboard designs (specially in Shiny), and agriculture.

Education

2014 - 2018 PhD in Statistics University of São Paulo -(4 years)

> Title: Estimating the longitudinal concordance correlation through fixed effects and variance components of polynomial mixed-effects regression model

Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi and Prof. John Hinde

Department of Exact Sciences

2016 Visiting scholar – internship (3 months)

NUIGalway

ESALQ/USP

■ Supervisor: Prof. John Hinde

School of Mathematics, Statistics and Applied Mathematics

▶ Development of new methodology in Concordance Analysis

2012 - 2014 (2 years)

MSc in Statistics

University of São Paulo -ESALQ/USP

Title: Mixed-effects models applied to hue peel color of papaya cv. Sunrise Solo measured by an scanner and colorimeter over time

Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi

Department of Exact Sciences

2007 - 2012 BSc in Agricultural Engineering (5 years)

University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP

- ▶ Title: Calibration of scanner methodology to evaluate 'Golden' papaya peel color.
- Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi
- ▶ Department of Exact Sciences

Professional experience

2019 (8 months)	Postdoc in Biostatistics	NUIGalway
	 Supervisor: Prof. Dr. John Newell Statistical modeling for optimizing athlete performance School of Mathematics, Statistics & Applied Maths; Orreco; and Analytics 	Insight Centre for Data
2018-2019 (10 months)	Postdoc in Statistics Un	niversity of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP
	 Advisor: Prof. Dr. Clarice Garcia Borges Demétrio Title: Estimation of the longitudinal concordance correlation function Department of Exact Sciences 	n: The lcc package
2017 - 2019	Assistant Professor at University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP (18 mont	ths)

Volunteer experience

2016	Class tutor in Calculus at University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP (5 months)
2015	Class tutor in Statistics at University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP (5 months)

Research experience

G	ieneralized linear mixed-effects models (Classical and Bayesian)
C	oncordance analysis (Agreement, precision, and accuracy measures)
В	cootstrap methods for confidence intervals (Non-parametric and parametric)
	xperimental Designs (Complete and Incomplete Blocks, Latin Square, Full factorial, ractional Factorial, Split-Plot, Central Composite, Nested designs)
Lo	ongitudinal data and Observational Studies
St	tate space models (ARMA, ARIMA and Random Walk models)
D	rigital Image Analysis, Vegetal Production, Post-Harvest
D	Development of R packages, Dashboard Design, and Webpages (Github)

Publications

Table 1: Publications summary				
	Article	R Package	Abstract	Manuscript
Number	4	1	6	2

Submitted manuscript

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R. A.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S. S.; Demetrio, C. G. B. Estimation of the longitudinal concordance correlation function in R: The LCC package. **Journal of Statistical Software**. Submitted in September 2019.

Submitted manuscript

Kleina, H. T.; Kudlawiec, K.; Esteves, M. B.; Daibó, M.; **Oliveira, T.P.**; Maluta, N.; Lopes, J. S.; Mio, L. M. Association of leaf morphology, vector settling and feeding behavior with resistence of plum genotypes to leaf scald disease. **Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata**. Submitted in September 2019.

Article

Popin, G. V.; Santos, A. K. B.; **Oliveira, T.P.**; Camargo, P. B.; Cerri, C. E. P.; Siqueira-Neto; M. Sugarcane straw management for bioenergy: effects of global warming on greenhouse gas emissions and soil carbon storage. **Mitigation and Adaptation Strategies for Global Change**, 2019. Link: https://doi.org/10.1007/s11027-019-09880-7

R package

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R. A.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S. S.; Demetrio, C. G. B. lcc: Longitudinal Concordance Correlation, R package version 1.0.2, 2018. See also https://github.com/Prof-ThiagoOliveira/lcc

Article

Esteves, M. B.; Kleina, H. T.; Sales, T. M.; **Oliveira, T.P.**; Lara, I. A. R.; Almeida, R. P. P.; Coletta-Filho, H. D.; Lopes, J. R. S. Transmission efficiency of *Xylella fastidiosa* subsp. *pauca* sequence types by sharpshooter vectors after *in vitro* acquisition. **The American Phytopathological Society**, v. 109, no.2, 2019. Link: https://doi.org/10.1094/PHYT0-07-18-0254-FI

Article

Oliveira, T.P.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S. S. Longitudinal Concordance Correlation Function Based on Variance Components: An Application in Fruit Color Analysis. **Journal of Agricultural, Biological, and Environmental Statistics**, v. 23, p. 233-254, 2018. Link: https://doi.org/10.1007/s13253-018-0321-1

Article

Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S. S.; Jacomino, A. P. Measuring color hue in 'Sunrise Solo' papaya using a flatbed scanner. **Revista Brasileira de Fruticultura**, v. 39, p. e-911, 2017. Link: http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/0100-29452017911

Extended abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R. A.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S. S.; Demétrio, C. G. B. The longitudinal concordance correlation. **In: 34**th **International Workshop on Statistical Modelling**, 2019, Guimarães. Proceedings of the 34th International Workshop on Statistical Modelling, 2019. v. 2.

Extended abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R. A.; Hinde, J.; Demétrio, C. G. B.; Zocchi, S. S.; Zanardo, A. B. R.; Delalibera Jr., I. Generalized linear mixed models applied to overdispersed proportion data in a fungal occurrence study. **In: 30**th **International Workshop on Statistical Modelling**, 2015, Linz. Proceedings of the 30th International Workshop on Statistical Modelling, 2015. v. 2. p. 203-206.

Abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R. A.; Hinde, J.; Demétrio, C. G. B.; Zocchi, S. S. Generalized linear mixed models: an application in fungal occurrence data. In: 60° Reunião Anual da Região Brasileira da Sociedade Internacional de Biometria e 16° Simpósio de Estatística Aplicada à Experimentação Agronômica, 2015, Presidente Prudente. Reunião Anual da Região Brasileira da Sociedade Internacional de Biometria, n. 60, Presidente Prudente, 2015. 172 p., 2015.

Abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S. S.; Ferreira, I. E. P. . Mixed models for analysis of hue peel colour of papaya (Carica papaya L.) cv. Sunrise Solo, measured along time by means of a scanner and a colorimeter. In: XXVII International Biometric Conference, 2014, Florence, Italy. Proceedings of XXVII International Biometric Conference, 2014. v. 1.

Extended abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S. S. . Análise de dados circulares com aplicação em tonalidade da cor de casca de mamão 'Sunrise Solo'. In: 58ª Reunião Anual da Região Brasileira da Sociedade Internacional de Biometria e 15° Simpósio de Estatística Aplicada à Esperimentação Agronômica, 2013, Campina Grande. Anais..., 2013. p. 202.

Abstract

Camara, G. M. S.; Oliveira, T.P.; Navarro, B. L.; Brigliadori, L. D. Crescimento e produtividade de soja em três arranjos espaciais. In: VI Congresso Brasileiro de Soja, 2012, Cuiabá-MT. Anais. Londrina-PR: Embrapa Soja, 2012. v. 1. p. 151-153.

Reviewer

2019 Biocontrol Science and Technology, Taylor & Francis Link

Number of papers reviewed: 1

Masters and PhD Examiners

Nascimento, C.O.; Lara, I.A.R. Analysis of color peel of the papaya cv. Sunrise Solo through 2019

of the mixed linear regression model. Thesis (Master's Degree in Statistics) - University of

São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil.

Awards

Honorable Mention at the 18th USP International Symposium of Undergraduate Research, 2010

University of São Paulo.

Extracurricular courses (last 5 years)

2019	Survival Analysis in R. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Building Web Applications in R with Shiny: Case Studies Course. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Building Dashboards with shinydashboard. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Building Web Applications in R with Shiny. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Introduction to Python. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Statistical Modeling in R (Part 1). DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Intermediate R. DataCamp, USA. (6h)
2019	Introduction to R. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2018	Machine Learning Toolbox. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2016	Longitudinal and Incomplete Data – USP (30h)
2015	Short curse on Regression Models – Coursera, MOOC, USA (36h)
2015	Short curse on Dimensionality Reduction – USP
2015	Additive Generalized Models with P-splines – RBras
2015	Exploring interactive graphical interfaces in R – RBras
2015	Exploring the Flexibility of Linear Mixed Models – RBras

2015	Special Topics in Multivariate Analysis – RBras
2014	Generalized Additive Models with P-splines – USP

>>> Event par	rticipation (last 5 years)
2019	The Inaugural Young-ISA Meeting – Maynooth, Co. Kildare, Ireland
2019	34^{th} meeting of the International Workshop on Statistical Modelling (IWSM) – Guimarães, Portugal.
2016	NUIG Statistics MiniSymposium. Longitudinal Concordance correlation function based on variance components: an application in fruit color analysis.
2015	30^{th} meeting of the International Workshop on Statistical Modelling (IWSM) – Linz, Vienna.
2015	60 th meeting of the Brazilian Region International Biometric Society (RBras) e 16° "Simpósio de Estatística Aplicada à Experimentação Agronômica" – Presidente Prudente, SP, Brazil
2015	How to Write for and Get Published in Scientific Journals – Piracicaba, SP, Brazil

II Workshop on Longitudinal and Incomplete Data - Piracicaba, SP, Brazil

Lectured disciplines

2014

2014

2018	LCE0120 Calculus I – ESALQ/USP
2018	LCE0602 Experimental Statistics – ESALQ/USP
2018	LCE0220 Calculus II – ESALQ/USP
2017	LCE0602 Experimental Statistics – ESALQ/USP
2017	LCE0120 Calculus II – ESALQ/USP

I Workshop on Experimental Statistics e IV "Encontro dos Alunos do PPG em Agronomia" -

Lectured workshops and invited talks

Piracicaba, SP, Brazil

2019	Modelling menstrual cycle length using state space models. The Inaugural Young-ISA Meeting – Maynooth, Ireland
2018	I Workshop on Introduction to Experimental Design – ESALQ/USP
2016	Longitudinal concondance correlation function based on variance components: an application in fruit color – NUI Galway

Professional websites

Github	https://github.com/Prof-ThiagoOliveira	Link
ІссАрр	https://prof-thiagooliveira.shinyapps.io/lccApp/	Link
Calculus	https://prof-thiagooliveira.github.io/calculus/	Link

Academic	https://prof-thiagooliveira.github.io/AcademicProfile/	Link
>>> Fellows	hip	
2011	São Paulo Research Foundation	FAPESP
	 Scientific initiation / Advisor: Prof. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi Process number: 2010/16955-1 Grants awarded: approximately £3.000 	
2012-2013	Coordination of Improvement of Higher Education Personnel	CAPES
	 Master / Advisor: Prof. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi Project: Mixed effects models applied to hue peel color of papaya (Carica pa"Sunrise Solo" measured over time using an scanner and a colorimeter Grants awarded: approximately £15.082 	apaya L.) cv.
2014-2017	National Council for Scientific and Technological Development	CNPq
	 PhD / Advisor: Prof. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi Project: Estimating the longitudinal concordance correlation through fixed effects components of polynomial mixed-effects regression model Grants awarded: approximately £26.543 	and variance
2018-2019	Coordination of Improvement of Higher Education Personnel	CAPES
	 Postdoctoral Researcher / Coordinator: Prof^a. Clarice G. B. Demétrio Project: Estimation of Longitudinal Concordance Correlation Function: The lcc Grants awarded: approximately £7.000 	package
2019	Science Foundation Ireland	SFI
	 Postdoctoral Researcher in Biostatistics / Coordinator: Prof. John Newell Project: Development of statistical model with application in athlete performance Project Funding: €12.417.097 	ee
>>> Referer	nces	
	Prof. John Hinde	NUIGalway

Prof. John Hinde	NUIGalway
Phone: +353 (0) 91 492043	
Email: john.hinde@nuigalway.ie	
Dr. Rafael de Andrade Moral	Maynooth University
▶ Phone: +353 (1) 708 6645	
▶ Email: rafael.deandrademoral@mu.ie	
Prof. John Newell	NUIGalway
▶ Phone: +353 (0) 91 524411	
▶ Email: john.newell@nuigalway.ie	

Prof. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi Phone:+55 (19) 3429.4127 Email: sszocchi@usp.br Prof. Clarice Garcia Borges Demétrio ESALQ/USP

Phone:+55 (19) 3429.4127Email: clarice.demetrio@usp.br